# Garreth Martin

# garreth DOT martin1 AT gmail DOT com

#### INFO

#### Address:

Centre for Astrophysics Research University of Hertfordshire College Lane Hertfordshire AL10 9AB United Kingdom

#### **EDUCATION**

PHD IN ASTROPHYSICS University of Hertfordshire 2015 – present Expected March 2019

MPHYS IN ASTROPHYSICS University of Hertfordshire 2011 – 2015 First Class with Honours Average grade 81%

## **SKILLS**

#### **PROGRAMMING**

Advanced
Python • IDL • Matlab • Shell • ATEX
Proficient
Fortran • Yorick • HTML • SQL

# **TOOLS**

Git • Linux • DS9 • MS Office • Noise Chisel • SExtractor • SUNRISE / SUNSET

## **AFFILIATIONS**

Member of the Institute of Physics Fellow of the Royal Astronomical Society

## LINKS

Website: garrethmartin.github.io Orchid: 0000-0003-2939-8668 ArXiv: a/martin\_g\_1 ADS: nThU2Yw3SUytqSYjksZ8uA

#### **SUMMARY**

I am a PhD student (3 years) at the University of Hertfordshire specialising in the evolution of galaxy morphology and the role of mergers. I am particularly interested in the interface between observational and theoretical astronomy, making predictions and developing theoretical tools for the effective exploitation of next generation instruments. My work spans a diverse array of disciplines, combining state-of-the-art hydrodynamical simulations and survey data with machine-learning techniques.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### KASI-ARIZONA JOINT POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW

2019 – present | Korea Astronomy and Space Science Institute / University of Arizona

#### **BALZAN FELLOW**

May - August 2019 | New College, University of Oxford

#### **PHD STUDENT**

**2015 – 2019 | University of Hertfordshire | Supervisor**: Dr Sugata Kaviraj **Thesis title**: On the key processes that drive galaxy evolution

- Studying the role of mergers and black holes on evolution of galaxies
- Using machine-learning and statistical techniques to develop theoretical tools and make predictions for effectively exploiting next-generation instruments

#### **SUMMER STUDENT**

April – July 2015 | University of Hertfordshire | Supervisor : Dr Marc Sarzi

• Developed tools to perform spectro-photometric SED fitting combining IFU data from MUSE with UV photometry

#### **TEACHING**

Nov 2016 - Mar 2018 'Programming' teaching assistant

- Taught students Python and Matlab for scientific programming
- Assisted students with programming exercises during practicals

## Nov 2016 - Mar 2017 'Physics of Stars' demonstrator

- Assisted students at the University's Bayfordbury teaching observatory
- Instructed students in the use of 16-inch telescopes and data reduction
- Practicals included open cluster CMDs, exoplanet transits and imaging PN

## Nov 2015 - Mar 2017 'Cosmology and Large Scale Structure' demonstrator

- Assisted students with practicals and taught a range of cosmological topics
- Practicals included calculating the Hubble constant, the mass of lensing clusters

## **OUTREACH**

Jun 2016 Big Bang Fair – Newmarket

• Demonstrated physical concepts by helping children do simple experiments

## 2015 - present Bayfordbury Observatory public open evenings

- Organised activities for a mix of children, adults and amateur astronomers
- Explained astronomy concepts to people from a range of backgrounds and ages

# **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

- Simulations : cosmological simulations of galaxy evolution post-processing mock observations theoretical predictions
- Galaxies: morphological evolution the emergence of the Hubble sequence low surface-brightness and ultra-diffuse galaxies the role of galaxy mergers the role of AGN
- Big data: large surveys unsupervised machine-learning techniques

#### Garreth Martin

## **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **PUBLISHED**

- \* The formation and evolution of low-surface-brightness galaxies, **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Laigle C., Devriendt J. E. G., Dubois Y., Pichon C., 2019, MNRAS, 485, 761.
- \* The role of mergers in driving morphological transformation over cosmic time, **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Devriendt J. E. G., Dubois Y., Pichon C., 2018, MNRAS, 480, 2266.
- \* Normal black holes in bulge-less galaxies: the largely quiescent, merger-free growth of black holes over cosmic time, **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Volonteri M., Simmons B. D., Devriendt J. E. G., Lintott C. J., Smethurst R. J., Dubois Y., Pichon C., 2018, MNRAS, 476, 2810.

Identifying the progenitors of present-day early-type galaxies in observational surveys: correcting 'progenitor bias' using the Horizon-AGN simulation, **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Devriendt J. E. G., Dubois Y., Pichon C., Laigle C., 2018, MNRAS, 474, 3140.

\* The limited role of galaxy mergers in driving stellar mass growth over cosmic time, **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Devriendt J. E. G, Dubois Y., Laigle C., Pichon C., 2017, MNRAS letters, 472, L50.

## SUBMITTED AND IN PREPARATION

AGN in dwarf galaxies: frequency, triggering processes and the plausibility of AGN feedback, Kaviraj S., **Martin G.**, Silk J., submitted to MNRAS.

Forming massive spheroidal galaxies via single minor mergers, Jackson R. A., **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Laigle C., Devriendt J. E. G., Dubois Y., Pichon C., submitted to MNRAS.

When Galaxies Align, Bate J., Chisari N. E., **Martin G.**, Codis S., Laigle C., Dubois Y., Devriendt J. E. G., Slyz A., Kaviraj S., Pichon C., Miller S., submitted to MNRAS.

A flat trend of star-formation rate with X-ray luminosity of galaxies hosting AGN in the SCUBA-2 Cosmology Legacy Survey, Ramasawmy J., Stevens J., Martin G., Geach J. E., submitted to MNRAS.

Why do extremely massive discs exist today?, Jackson R. A., **Martin G.**, Kaviraj S., Laigle C., Devriendt J. E. G., Dubois Y., Pichon C., Shabala S., in prep.

An automated census of galaxy morphology in the HSC-SSP survey, Martin G., Kaviraj S., Hocking A., Geach J., in prep.

# CONFERENCE TALKS AND SEMINARS

Astronomy Group Lunchtime Talk in St Andrews, UK, February 2019 (invited talk)

Cosmology Group Seminar in Jerusalem, Israel, January 2019 (invited seminar)

Ramses User Meeting in Lyon, France, September 2018 (contributed talk)

The Bewildering Nature of Ultra-diffuse Galaxies in Leiden, Netherlands, August 2018 (invited talk)

Santa Cruz Galaxy Workshop in Santa-Cruz, USA, August 2018 (contributed talk)

Wetton Workshop - Data Driven Discovery in the era of Large Data in Oxford, UK, June 2018 (contributed talk)

National Astronomy Meeting / European Week of Astronomy in Liverpool, UK, April 2018 (contributed talk)

From Micrometers to Megaparsecs in Southampton, UK, March 2018 (contributed talk)

Black hole formation and growth in Saas-Fee, Switzerland, January 2018 (poster)

New frontiers in Galaxy Evolution Modelling in London, UK, October 2017 (invited talk)

Ramses User Meeting in Nice, France, September 2017 (contributed talk)

A Broadband Look at Astrophysical Processes in Southampton, UK, March 2017 (poster)

National Astronomy Meeting in Hull, UK, July 2017 (contributed talk)

Galaxy Evolution Seminar in Oxford, UK, June 2017 (invited seminar)

Ramses User Meeting in Paris. France, October 2016 (contributed talk)

Deconstructing Galaxies at Cosmic Noon in Leiden, Netherlands, August 2016 (contributed talk)

## SCIENTIFIC ORGANISING COMMITTEES

**Galaxy-Black Hole Co-evolution: Observational and Theoretical Perspectives** National Astronomy Meeting in Lancaster, UK, July 2019

#### GRANTS AND AWARDS

2019 University Student Trust PGR conference funding, £460

2018 Balzan travelling fellowship, New College, Oxford (May - July 2019) - accommodation and subsistence for 10 weeks.

2018 Royal Astronomical Society small grants scheme, £600

- **2017** Royal Astronomical Society small grants scheme, £375
- **2016** Royal Astronomical Society small grants scheme, £400
- 2015 University of Hertfordshire Patrick Moore Prize for best overall performance in cohort
- $\textbf{2012} \ \ \textbf{University of Hertfordshire Scholarship}, \textbf{£}1500$

# MAJOR COLLABORATIONS

- 2017 present Junior associate LSST galaxies collaboration (full LSST data rights)
- 2016 present ANR SPIN(e) Cosmic origin of Hubble sequence
- 2016 present Member of the Horizon simulation project